A Guide to the Bethlehem Stone Church Records, 1844-1980s
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Special Collections, James Madison University
Bethlehem Stone Church Records, 1844-1980s
Special Collections, James Madison University
SC 5037
5,430 digital images
The Bethlehem Christian Church Records is a digital collection that contains scans of documents relating to the church from its inception in 1844 through the 1980s. There are minutes of business meetings and Sunday Schools, financial accounts, lists of members, and general historical information.
Bethlehem United Methodist Church of Christ, Tenth Legion, Virginia
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None
Acquisition Information
Documents lent to James Madison Special Collections for digitization in 2012.
Provenance
Acquiring the collection was suggested to Mark Peterson, head of James Madison Special Collections, by Dr. Andrew Witmer. Dr. Witmer intended to include the collection in his History Harvest project but was unable to do so because of time constraints. Dr. Peterson contacted the church and, with the help of the church’s secretary, gathered the collection for digitization in 2012.
Biographical Information
Bethlehem United Church of Christ, commonly called the Bethlehem Stone Church, sits in Tenth Legion, just south of New Market, Virginia in the Shenandoah Valley. Today the church campus consists of a small stone building and a larger brick building. The stone structure was the original house of worship for the Bethlehem congregation and was constructed in 1845, one year after its founding. Since that time Bethlehem United Church of Christ has had an active congregation that has held church dinners, homecomings, regular Sunday worship, and Sunday School. During the Civil War the Old Stone Church was used as a military hospital and during a restoration of the building in 2008 the names of many soldiers were found penciled on the walls. After the Civil War the church was used by several different denominations including the Christian Church, the United Brethren in Christ, and the German Baptist Church. The structure itself was in need of repair from neglect and damage done during the Civil War. In 1872 a committee was formed to reorganize the congregation and repair the Church’s structural damage. The congregation worshipped in the Stone Church until 1952 when a larger brick church was built on the land beside it. Since that time the congregation has continued worship on the property and has shown interest in its rich history. In 1981 Bethlehem Stone Church was added to the Virginia Landmarks Register and in 2008 the congregation, with support from the community, restored the Stone Church.
Scope and Content
The Bethlehem Stone Church Records consist of 5,430 digital images. These images have been arranged according to theme into five series. The following is a breakdown of each series with a short description of the various documents:
Series I: Business/Treasurer’s Minutes
Church Begins 1844… (1844-1873) This book notes where church services were held and who was present. It includes a roll of all the male and female members and their standing within the church.
Deed 1844 Two (1881-1886) The first page of the document labels this book as “Bethlehem, Va Christian Church Book.” It details the governing principles of the church in 1881, a roll of members, minutes of meetings, and the original deed for the church land.
1892 E.T. Isley/1895 R.H. Peel (1881-1895) This notebook is filled with general notes as to the business of the church. It includes membership records as well as accounts of how much money each member contributed to the pastor’s salary. Lists of annual committee officers are listed as well as minutes of business meetings.
1883 Three (1884-1894) Business and treasury minutes are noted here. There are listings of receipts and debts paid, and the organization of Sabbath School (Sunday School).
1896 R.H. Peel-1910 Rev. W.T. Walters (1896-1910) Like many of the other business records, this notebook lists the officers of the church, a roll of the members, and business minutes of Conference meetings.
Treasurer (1897-1898)-check date Records of church members and their payments to the pastor’s salary.
Ledger (1906-1915) The ledger includes apportionment records and general treasury and accounting information.
Va Valley Central Christian Conference Treasure Book (1912-1924) A treasurer’s account of various committees within the conference such as the Woman's Home and Foreign Mission Board.
Tithing Record (1919-1926) This is a record of tithing for members of the church starting in 1919 running through 1926.
Church Record (c. 1940s) Conference minutes, indexes of church members, and attendance records are included in this record.
Annual Report to Conference (1944-1945) An accounting of the contemporary composition of the church such as who was pastor—Rev. G.H. Beazey—his history, the total membership, and the church’s finances.
Proposed Budget for 1946-1947 (1946-1947) The details of this document spell out the proposed budget for 1946 and 1947. Some of the categories are the pastor’s salary, parsonage rent, pew payments, janitor services, etc.
Payment of Parsonage Debt per Church (1948) This payment record lists the debts of various parsonages for things like plumbing, property repairs, and the building of garages. Bethlehem United Church of Christ is one of the churches listed on this report.
A Decision From Bethlehem… (5 December 1950) A letter that details the reasons behind Reverend Clyde O’Koon's resignation.
Church Business Meeting Minutes (1948-1952) These minutes relate details of the monthly business meetings. They were opened with prayer and discussed issues like salaries, building additions to the church and arrangements for Home Coming.
On March 4, 1952 (1952) In 1952 Bethlehem United Church of Christ hosted the twenty-second mid-year session of the Virginia Valley Central Conference of Congregational-Christian Churches. This document relates the members elected to this particular conference.
WriteRight (1952-1954) This book is filled with monthly business meeting notes for the church.
Series II: Sunday School Minutes Each of these documents contains minutes of Sunday School meetings. They detail the people elected to committee positions, a roll of members in the classes, a list of classes, a weekly program of the meetings that includes songs, scriptures and a few business notes. Any exception to this has been noted.
S.S. Records 1896-1903 (1896-1903) S.S. stands for Sunday School.
Sunday School Records 1907-1912 (1907-1912)
SE Ledger S. S. Treasurer 1913-1914 (1913-1914) This is a cash account of the Bethlehem Sunday School’s collection. There are a few business meeting minutes at the end.
Sunday School Minutes 1938-1940 (1938-1940) Rosalie F. Sellers gave these minutes to Bethlehem United Church of Christ in 1988.
S.S. Records 9/1/1940-7/25/1943 (1940-1943)
Record 1943-1946 Pauline Brown Shope gave these records to Bethlehem Church on July 7, 1986.
Sunday School Minutes 1948-1952 (1948-1952)
The 1950 Supernatural Notebook (1950-1951) Less formal in organization than all previous Sunday School records.
100 pages composition (1931-1934) This composition notebook includes notes and accounts for expenses and profits of soup sales, election dinners, and Mid-Conference Dinners. Menus for these dinners are included. A woman’s group within the church organized these meals and fundraisers at the church.
Ladies' Aid-Minutes of Meetings (1936-1942) The Ladies' Aid Committee met monthly at various members' homes and organized things such as raffles, and benevolent aid missions. They would buy oil cloth for tables, get the piano in the church tuned, write cards for convalescents, and send out fruit baskets. This document is the minutes of their meetings.
History of Women’s Fellowship of Valley of Va (1938) This is a typed history report of the Valley Conference. There is one report of Bethlehem that mentions the Conference at Bethlehem. It mentions the work that they did in organizing the Conference Missionary Association. Most of the information is about the women’s missionary conference, but men are mentioned as well.
Program Booklet (1965-1966) Program Booklet for Lay Life and Work of Bethlehem United Church of Christ. This annual booklet was created by and for the Women’s Fellowship Committee. It’s theme for 1965-1966 was “Mission: The Christian's Calling.” It includes an index of sections that consist of a lesson plans for a bible study. There is also a list of officers and leaders for the Committee. It is essentially a reference guide or a program for the upcoming year.
Program Booklet (1966-1967) This is the same as the above booklet but it has no stated theme.
Program Booklet (1967-1968) Theme: “Living our faith in Today’s Walk”
Program Booklet ((1968-1969) Theme: "Facing the New Day
Program Booklet (1969-1970) Theme: "Bring the Good News"
Program Booklet (1970-1971) Theme: "Love is"
Program Booklet Theme: "Do According to Your Faith"(1971-1972)
Program Booklet (1972-1973) Theme: "As You Go"
Program Booklet (1974-1975) No theme stated
Women’s Fellowship Binder (1959-1968) This is a binder filled with minutes from the Ladies' Aid Meetings. They would gather together, have a devotional, and then hold a meeting. Their minutes reveal that their work included organizing church suppers, giving gifts to orphans they were sponsoring, and buying supplies for the church kitchen.
Women’s Fellowship Binder (1969-1975) Like the previous Women’s Fellowship Binder, this binder holds minutes for the women’s committee at the church. Unlike the previous binder the name of this committee changed from the Ladies' Aid Meetings to the Women’s Fellowship of Bethlehem. The committee did the same sorts of charitable work and fund-raising as before.
Series IV: Church History Many of the documents in these history collections are duplicates of one another. For example, files numbers 5037.2.1628, 1752, 1753, 1826, 1998, and 2024 are each the same document referring to changes in the architectural structure of the church building.
Newspaper Scrapbook- “Perfection” This scrapbook contains newspaper clippings that mention Bethlehem United Christian Church and its members. There is a focus on obituaries. An inscription on the interior of the document tells us that the scrapbook was made by Miss Ella (Ella Pickering) and given to the church upon her death.
Memories Binder This is a collection of documents relating to the history of the church. There are typed histories of the church, images of members and activities on the grounds, details of changes to the church architecture, and lists of pastors.
Church History Folder This folder also contains newspaper clippings and photographs related to the church. It also has several program bulletins for the 145th anniversary celebration of worship, a church directory, and the addresses of many members.
Church Papers Folder Here are more miscellaneous items concerning church history.
Church History Additional Folder Similar to the above history folders. This one contains a history of the parsonage for the church, and landscape plans for the back yard/parking lot of the church.
History Info Folder This contains a brief history of Bethlehem Christian Church, more typed histories, and newspaper clippings.
Miscellaneous Papers-Bethlehem Miscellaneous papers about the church that includes newspaper clippings, images, and more typed histories of the church. There are also images of soldiers names penciled on to the church wall from the Civil War.
National Historic Marker Info Folder (1980s) During the 1980s the church put forth a nomination form for the Church’s addition to the National Register of Historic Places. The documents in this folder are the nomination forms and letters pertaining to this process which was successful.
Series V: Miscellaneous
Record Book-Book I Deaths Rena Foltz (1915-1979) An inscription on the back of the front cover tells us that Rena Foltz wrote this record book between 1915 and 1979, and it was donated to the church by her daughter at Rena’s death. It lists people who died, when, at what age, who their family was, and sometimes where they are buried.
Record Book-Book II Deaths Rena Foltz Same information as the above Record Book of Deaths.
Historic Garden Week (1984) In 1984 Bethlehem United Christian Church was included in the Historic Garden Week Tour. As such, it had an entry in the event’s book which was donated to the church. The entry for Bethlehem is on page 58, file 5037.2.1188.
Geography Questions This document contains a hand written play, poems, and trivia about American geography.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in 5 series:
I: Business/Treasurer's Minutes
II: Sunday School Records
III: Women's Business
IV: Church History
V: Miscellaneous
Contents List
- Business/Treasurer's Minutes1844-1954
  - Church Begins 1844 1844-1873, Image 5037.2.001-5037.2.108
  - Deed 1844 Two1881-1886, Image 5037.2.132-5037.2.304
  - 1892 E.T. Isley/1895 R.H. Peel 1881-1895, Image 5037.3.999-5037.3.1127
  - 1883 Tree 1884-1894, Image 5037.2.305-5037.2.444
  - 1896 R.H. Peel-1910 Rev. W.T. Walters 1896-1910, Image 5037.3.1130-5037.3.1272
  - Treasurer 1897-1898, Image 5037.2.1357-5037.2.1468
  - Ledger 1906-1915, Image 5037.3.320-5037.3.627
  - VA Valley Central Christian Conference Treasure Book 1912-1924, Image 5037.3.630-5037.3.697
  - Tithing Record 1919-1926, Images 5037.3.2037-5037.3.319; 5037.3.061-5037.3.065
  - Church Record c. 1940s, Image 5037.3.1410-5037.3.1664
  - Annual Report to Conference 1944-1945, Image 5037.2.115-5037.2.118
  - Proposed Budget for 1946-1947, Image 5037.2.109-5037.2.110
  - Payment of Parsonage Debt per Church 1948, Image 5037.2.119-5037.2.122
  - A Decision from Bethlehem 1950 December 05, Image 5037.2.113-5037.2.114
  - Church Business Meetings 1948-1952, Image 5037.3.003-5037.3.060
  - On March 5, 1952, Image 5037.2.111-5037.2.112
  - WriteRight 1952-1954, Image 5037.2.1042-5037.2.1095
- Sunday School Records 1896-1951
  - S.S. Records 1896-1903, Image 5037.3.180-5037.3.996
  - Sunday School Records 1907-1912, Image 5037.3.1280-5037.3.1402
  - SE Ledger S.S. Treasurer 1913-1914, Image 5037.3.700-5037.3.779
  - Sunday School Minutes 1938-1940, Image 5037.2.445-5037.2.527
  - S.S. Records 1940 September 09-1943 July 25, Image 5037.2.773-5037.2.9914
  - Record 1943-1946, Image 5037.2.573-5037.2.772
  - Sunday School Minutes 1948-1952, Image 5037.3.066-5037.3.200
  - The 1950 Supernatural Notebook 1950-1951, Image 5037.2.992-5037.2.1041
- Women's Business 1931-1975
  - 100 Page Composition 1931-1934, Image 5037.1.001-5037.1.072
  - Ladies Aid-Minutes of Meetings 1936-1942, Image 5037.1.081-5037.1.192
  - History of VA Women's Fellowship of Valley of VA 1938, Image 5037.2.1284-5037.2.1356
  - Program Booklet 1965-1966, Image 5037.1.201-5037.1.217
  - Program Booklet 1966-1967, Image 5037.1.228-5037.1.243
  - Program Booklet 1967-1968, Image 5037.1.252-5037.1.272
  - Program Booklet 1968-1969, Image 5037.1.281-5037.1.302
  - Program Booklet 1969-1970, Image 5037.1.311-5037.1.329
  - Program Booklet 1970-1971, Image 5037.1.341-5037.1.364
  - Program Booklet 1971-1972, Image 5037.1.375-5037.1.397
  - Program Booklet 1972-1973, Image 5037.1.408-5037.1.427
  - Program Booklet 1974-1975, Image 5037.1.438-5037.1.449
  - Women's Fellowship Binder 1959-1968, Image 5037.1.553-5037.1.1017
  - Women's Fellowship Binder 1969-1975, Image 5037.1.1020-5037.1.1374
- Church History
  - Newspaper Scrapbook, Image 5037.1.1805-5037.1.1852
  - Memories Binder, Image 5037.2.1546-5037.2.1682
  - Church History Folder, Image 5037.2.1684-5037.2.1888
  - Church Papers Folder, Image 5037.2.1890-5037.2.1908
  - Church History Additional Folder, Image 5037.2.1910-5037.2.1988
  - History Info Folder, Image 5037.2.1990-5037.2.2030
  - Miscellaneous Papers- Bethlehem, Image 5037.2.2080-5037.2.2122
  - National Historic Marker Info 1980s, Image 5037.2.2032-5037.2.2077
- Miscellaneous 1915-1984
  - Record Book- Book I Deaths Rena Foltz 1915-1979, Image 5037.1.1380-5037.1.1589
  - Record Book- Book II Deaths Rena Foltz, Image 5037.1.1591-5037.1.803
  - History Garden Week 1984, Image 5037.2.1096-5037.2.1283
  - Geography Questions, Image 5037.2.1470-5037.2.1544